<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Electronics | Silvio Gregorini</title>
    <link>https://s-gregorini003.github.io/tag/electronics/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://s-gregorini003.github.io/tag/electronics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Electronics</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Silvio Gregorini © 2021 </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 08:45:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://s-gregorini003.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Electronics</title>
      <link>https://s-gregorini003.github.io/tag/electronics/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>3D Printed Acoustic Absorbers</title>
      <link>https://s-gregorini003.github.io/project/3d-printed-absorbers/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 08:45:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://s-gregorini003.github.io/project/3d-printed-absorbers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This blog post is to summarise a research project conducted at the beginning of 2019 as part of the Advanced Audio Engineering module (MSc Audio Engineering, Leeds Beckett University). The project discusses the potential of achieving high performance in terms of sound absorption through additive manufacturing techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The absorbers are designed to exploit the principle of passive destructive interference (PDI) and manufactured using a commercially available fused deposition modeling (FDM) 3D printer. The specimen are cylindrical and produced with cavities of different lengths. The absorption coefficient is evaluated using an impedance tube and following the specifications of the standard &lt;a href=&#34;https://shop.bsigroup.com/ProductDetail?pid=000000000030069842&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BS EN ISO 10534-2:2001&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results show that significant sound absorption can be achieved, although some absorption peaks do not match the expected frequencies. This may be caused by turbulence and resonance phenomena, especially in samples with greater diameter of the cavity. Futher investigation is required, but the potential of these technologies in terms of efficiency over manufacturing cost and absorber size is undoubted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of the project is to design and manufacture Passive Destructive Interference (PDI) absorbers using Additive Manufacturing (AM) techniques and then to evaluate their performance through a low cost, self-built impedance tube. The main outcome of the measurement process is a set of diagrams of the normal absorption factor of the specimens as a function of frequency in a mid-low spectrum range. The sound absorption curves will be then analyzed to determine the effects of the tested geometries and to verify if the experimental results agree with the values expected from the samples in the design phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;theory-and-methodology&#34;&gt;Theory and Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investigated devices are designed to absorb specific frequencies through passive destructive interference. These frequencies depend mainly on the specimen&amp;rsquo;s geometry, and can be calculated in advance through the following equation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$f_n = \frac{(2n - 1)* c}{2L}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;em&gt;L&lt;/em&gt; (m) is the length of the cavity and &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt; (m/s) is the speed of sound in the air.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-specification-and-design-of-a-specimen&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://s-gregorini003.github.io/project/3d-printed-absorbers/sample-A-specs.png&#34; alt=&#34;Specification and design of a specimen.&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Specification and design of a specimen.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I designed the samples in SolidWorks and manufactured with an AthorBot Brother Desktop 3D Printer. To test different materials, both geometries were printed in ABS and PETG.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-two-specimen-used-for-measurement&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://s-gregorini003.github.io/project/3d-printed-absorbers/specimen1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Two specimen used for measurement.&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable width=&#34;600px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Two specimen used for measurement.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The measurement of the absorption coefficient was conducted according to the &lt;em&gt;two-micophone technique&lt;/em&gt; detailed in &lt;a href=&#34;https://shop.bsigroup.com/ProductDetail?pid=000000000030069842&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BS EN ISO 10534-2:2001&lt;/a&gt;. The biggest issue faced in this project was to find an impedance tube to conduct the evaluation. Since my university had part of the equipment (microphones, soundcard, speakers&amp;hellip;), in the end I decided to build a low-cost impedance tube. I built it out of pvc pipes, hydraulic seals, and I added an Arduino Uno with an OLED display and temperature/humidity sensors to keep track of the environmental conditions. To calibrate the tube and conduct the measuring process - which consisted in measuring the cross-transfer function and then calculating the absorption coefficient - I used the software &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.holmarc.com/softwares/impedance_tube_software.rar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Holmarc Wave Analyzer 4C &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-measurement-test-equipment-layout&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://s-gregorini003.github.io/project/3d-printed-absorbers/TestEquipmentDiagram.png&#34; alt=&#34;Measurement test equipment layout.&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable width=&#34;800px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Measurement test equipment layout.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;findings&#34;&gt;Findings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For each specimen, measurements are taken in the frequency interval 100-3200 Hz. The normal sound absorption curves are analysed through the evaluation of two values:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The frequency of peak sound absorption&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The frequency range between the values on both sides of the peak where half the peak sound absorption occurs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using those values, the effects of the tested geometries can be determined and compared to the expected theoretical values. The results show that significant sound absorption has been achieved. The sound absorption coefficient reaches values of 0.87 at peak frequencies in the range considered. However, it must be noted that the absorption bandwidth is relatively narrow and that many relatively lower peaks can be attributed to the unprofessional measuring equipment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, the following figure shows that the predicted frequency of the peaks for sample A is respected mainly in the lower range, while they are slightly shifted in the mid-upper range considered, probably due to production defects in the specimen.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-measured-absorption-coefficient-for-sample-a-compared-to-predicted-peak-frequencies&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://s-gregorini003.github.io/project/3d-printed-absorbers/sample-A-results.png&#34; alt=&#34;Measured absorption coefficient for sample A compared to predicted peak frequencies.&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Measured absorption coefficient for sample A compared to predicted peak frequencies.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading! If you want to have a look at the full article, you can find it &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/343628647_Measurement_of_the_Absorption_Coefficient_for_Destructive_Interference_Absorbers_Produced_by_Additive_Manufacturing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/281005456_Sound_absorption_and_additive_manufacturing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sound absorption and additive manufacturing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.emerald.com/insight/content/doi/10.1108/13552540710824805/full/html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Implications of solid freeform fabrication on acoustic absorbers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>volca_boy[1] // Initial Design</title>
      <link>https://s-gregorini003.github.io/post/volca-boy-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 18:01:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://s-gregorini003.github.io/post/volca-boy-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;important-notice&#34;&gt;IMPORTANT NOTICE&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unfortunately, due to the Covid-19 pandemic, this project is currently paused.  The reason is that I had to leave my house in Leeds and temporarily return to my hometown in Italy, leaving most of my stuff in the UK. I really hope to go back as soon as possible and continue this journey.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;do-more-with-less&#34;&gt;Do More, with Less&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those unfamiliar with the term, &lt;em&gt;chiptune&lt;/em&gt; (also known as chipmusic, micromusic or 8-bit music) is a style of electronic music derived from the sound chips that, in the first generation of computers and gaming consoles, were used to balance the processing power of generating sound effects and music from the CPU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primal micromusic spirit was to overcome limitations and wield them in wildly creative ways. - &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fabiobortolotti/status/1267093927800139777&#34; title=&#34;Chiptune is dead. Here&amp;#39;s what I think.&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fabio &amp;ldquo;Kenobit&amp;rdquo; Bortolotti&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like everything nowadays, that definition can be interpreted in many ways. In its strictiest meaning, chiptune is used to refer to music created entirely from the original, vintage audio chips (nevertheless, modifications that do not alter the nature of the sound produced are &amp;ldquo;allowed&amp;rdquo;, but we&amp;rsquo;ll come back to this later). On the other hand, the broadest definition is more related to the aesthetics of the sound, rather then to the source generating it. In general, the philosophy behind the chiptune movement is to exploit the limited resources of the hardware to create more and more articulated music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;dmg-01&#34;&gt;DMG-01&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With its four audio channels, the &lt;em&gt;Game Boy&lt;/em&gt; is supposedly the most popular tool for the production of micromusic. This console has been around for quite some time (Nintendo released it in 1989), and over the course of the years many people created and documented mods to equip it with useful features for the cause, such as better audio, rechargeable battery, backlit screen&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;Channel&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Features&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pulse&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Volume envelope, 4-mode pulse width, frequency register from C3 upwards, frequency envelope&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pulse&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Volume envelope, 4-mode pulse width, frequency register from C3 upwards&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wave&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;User-definable waveforms, bank of 32 samples (4-bit each), frequency register from C2 upwards&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Noise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;White and brown noise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I want to do with this project is to use some of these mods as a starting point to transform that portable device into a proper music production tool, without over-denaturing its essence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-design&#34;&gt;First Design&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, I started this project as a university assignment, which is why I was able to document everything in detail (specifically, in this &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/s-gregorini003/interfaces-and-interactivity&#34; title=&#34;Interfaces and Interactivity&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Github repo&lt;/a&gt;). Back then, my idea was to tear apart a Game Boy, rewire it from the inside to a different controls and put everything into a new, original case.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-3d-model-made-with-solidworks-to-show-the-exploded-view-of-the-final-product&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://s-gregorini003.github.io/post/volca-boy-1/volca-boy-exploded-view.png&#34; alt=&#34;3D model made with SolidWorks to show the exploded view of the final product.&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      3D model made with SolidWorks to show the exploded view of the final product.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, towards the end of the semester I realised that creating a custom shell for my product was a task way harder than expected. So, after many stressful weeks, I decided - in accordance with my lecturers - to give up with the enclosure and present only a working prototype. Anyway, the exam went well, but I still want to bring this project to an end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collins, K. and Kapralos, B. and Tessler, H. and Paul, J. L. (2014) &lt;em&gt;The Oxford Handbook of Interactive Audio.&lt;/em&gt; Oxford: Oxford University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>volca_boy[0] // Project Summary</title>
      <link>https://s-gregorini003.github.io/project/volca-boy-0/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2020 16:13:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://s-gregorini003.github.io/project/volca-boy-0/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;important-notice&#34;&gt;IMPORTANT NOTICE&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unfortunately, due to the Covid-19 pandemic, this project is currently paused. The reason is that I had to leave my house in Leeds and temporarily return to my hometown in Italy, leaving most of my stuff in the UK. I really hope to go back as soon as possible and continue this journey.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volca Boy is a modding project aimed at turning a 1989 Game Boy into a portable synthesizer/sequencer. Although most of the work is original and designed by me, I borrowed some mods and code from other open source projects. In that case, I will give all the necessary credits to the modders from which I borrowed. This project is open source too, so feel free to try it, modify it, add and remove things to it as you like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The links will appear as the project progresses and the steps get documented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s-gregorini003.github.io/post/volca-boy-1/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mods Overview&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Software&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hardware - Electrical&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hardware - Case&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Demo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
