<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pages | ethok</title>
    <link>/page/</link>
      <atom:link href="/page/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Pages</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 13:03:37 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Pages</title>
      <link>/page/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>/page/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 13:03:37 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/page/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My name is &lt;strong&gt;Silvio Gregorini&lt;/strong&gt;, I am an engineer and aspiring researcher interested in how machine learning can be applied to deploy innovative digital music tools. I graduated from Leeds Beckett University with an MSc in Audio Engineering and received the &amp;ldquo;Solid State Logic Award for Highest Achieving Postgraduate Student&amp;rdquo;. I passed with Distinction with a thesis titled &lt;em&gt;Small-Footprint Keyword Spotting System for Low Power Applications Using Convolutional Neural Networks&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;future-aims&#34;&gt;Future Aims&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am currently looking for a PhD program starting in 2021 in machine learning for digital musical instruments, augmented/virtual reality, machine audition or 3D printing applications. I am also considering to undertake internships, either before or whilst researching.
If you would like to arrange a meeting, please &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:silvio.gregorini@outlook.com&#34;&gt;contact me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;in-short-i-try-to&#34;&gt;In short, I try to:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do my part in building the best sci-fi future possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have fun in the process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep learning new things that push my curiosity forward.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;previous-achievements&#34;&gt;Previous Achievements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I completed the following MOOCs on Coursera:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://coursera.org/share/d7622e4151c541ad2476837b524214d5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;TensorFlow in Practice Specialization&lt;/a&gt; by Deeplearning.ai&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://coursera.org/share/afdf9bb56bce7d9c91a3a90d8382a69d&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt; by Stanford University.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I designed and developed the Infrastructural Control Electronic System (ICES) for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gp2.info/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GP2 S.r.l.&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2018, I obtained a BSc degree in Mechanical and Materials Engineering at the University of Brescia (Italy), with a grade of 93/110 (equivalent to a 2:1 Honours) and a thesis titled &lt;em&gt;CoCr Alloys for Biomedical Applications Produced by Additive Manufacturing: Overview on Processes, Properties and Applications&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of my Bachelors, I worked as an intern at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.qpro.it/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;QPRO S.r.l.&lt;/a&gt;. My tasks were to perform quality assurance on 3D printed metal components and to help with the maintenance of an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eos.info/en/additive-manufacturing/3d-printing-metal&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;EOS M280&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-interests&#34;&gt;Other Interests&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alongside the academic work, I have various passions and interests that often intertwine. Some of them are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3D printing&lt;/strong&gt; - Probably the interest most linked with all the others. With a 3D printer you can basically make everything.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video Games&lt;/strong&gt; - Both modern and retro gaming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chiptune&lt;/strong&gt; - I restore and mod old consoles (mostly Game Boys) to compose and play music.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Music&lt;/strong&gt; - I play drums and produce electronic music. Guitar and bass are still a work in progress.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
